software engineering radio episode 86
interview with Dave Thomas
[Music]
okay welcome listeners to another
episode of software engineering radio
this is an hour episode we are recording
here at Uppsala 2007 and we have a guest
for this episode so there's an interview
and our guest is Dave Thomas
welcome to the show Dave my pleasure to
be with you great thanks
so why don't you introduce yourself to
our audience okay so this is Dave Thomas
the old country programmer eclipse day
for small talk Dave not Ruby Dave all
right I've I really appreciate that you
know the other Dave Thomas as such right
such wonderful books because he does
great brand maintenance I'm the old one
right and and you're among other things
that the founder of oti that's probably
what you're maybe most known for I'm
probably the most infamous before yes so
oti stands for object technology
international I guess yes sir obviously
you're quite a bit into object
technology so what do you think what
what about the state of object
technology these days well I mean it's
now 25 years from the introduction of
sort of early commercial object
technology and 40 years since Simula
which is the original technology which
shows you how long it takes for a good
idea to get to the street 20 years seems
to be a common number or at least a
generation that's maybe the point the
Chinese generation well also maturing in
the technology and things like that so I
think object technology is still a very
very important paradigm and a way to
provide modularity and to allow people
to put things together however I think
due to the complexity of the current
popular technologies and the lack of
time training investment that often at
least with the particularly with the
current technologies you know objects
are probably in the case of c-sharp and
jab in many cases at least for
businesses and some engineering
organizations creating a legacy that's
probably as bad or worse than the
previous technologies but I think you
know
it's clearly a benefit and clearly can
work I think frameworks were a really
bad idea I mean I'm really because
basically frameworks are very hard to
design they're really really a DSL the
really domain-specific language encoded
without in an object structure and and
that's of so language design in itself
is very hard and the problem is that
because you don't encapsulate the
framework in terms of components you get
all sorts of accidental coupling and
complexity where someone has to
basically understand a lot more about
the framework than they should to be
able to use it as a component and and
there was so many for so many people
excited essentially sort of framework so
kind of half-finished works right in
many cases but in there intentionally so
so they're they're great when used by
the framework experts when you can ship
them out they become pretty difficult to
use and you know normal people shouldn't
have to live inside a framework they
should be able to just use it more like
a component or a service so do you think
this is that the problems come from the
fact that you try to shoehorn something
that should be a language in 200 things
so do you think building dsls I have to
ask my building vs else is kind of the
more promising approach or is it
inherent in the problem that there is a
domain you have to understand and it's
inherently how to abstract the domain
and build something that expresses the
domain I think that framework design
because it isn't effectively a kind of
language design is hard
I think designing a good language is
hard at least it takes a different skill
set then someone who that is building
applications and so I think object
technology helps you but I also think
that that some of the language is make
it more difficult
I mean clearly in a language like Ruby
or small talk the the distance between
the DSL and the implementation is fairly
short versus if you're doing other
things then you have to generate a lot
more stuff and you have to understand
the generated stuff because you can't
debug it at the level of the
abstractions right
my impression is that object technology
is good for low-level design like stuff
but it's not an architectural paradigm
because it's a different level of
granularity and on the architectural
level people talk more about components
what do you think about that I mean
components were the next big thing after
objects
did they fulfill the promises I think we
got rushed in and we shipped frameworks
we didn't ship components okay and I
think that largely had to do with the
economics I think there was a great
opportunity miss than that someone
should have started the intel of
software components and built the
components that were very robust and
people have demonstrated in small ways I
mean from tcp/ip stacks to you know
widgets and things like that my people
will buy components I think if people
had actually invested in component
engineering the way they do for silicon
that we could we could have a lot better
quality components now but there was a
belief that a lot more people could do
this and so I think we kind of rushed
out the the technology and and the
frameworks I don't think we understood
how hard it was I mean the reality is
that for a lot of people even an easy
language like small talk is still hard
the interaction processes and things
like that so and the difference between
components and frameworks from your
perspective is probably black box versus
white or grey box right yes I mean I
think the reality is that everything is
a grey box but you definitely you know
today it's white box so that's and the
boundaries are not clear so yeah a clear
interface so I mean I think that while
the Eclipse process is something called
API first which is essentially you know
you define the architecture through a
set of api's and these are concrete
classes or you know they can be they can
be done with the special language thing
like interfaces if you have it they're
really part of the architecture and
they're in there and they're versioned
and they're very deep and they're really
they're really solid boundaries that
people don't cross how do you think that
SOA provides the right step in the right
direction and maybe you like formal
formal contracts and decoupling and and
and I'm not talking about web service
isn't that technology stuff rather about
the architectural style of so ah there's
also I have an architectural style well
that's what people say I mean it's
clearly something different from just
using whistle and soap there is more to
it and maybe I think I think by the time
anybody gets anything built with the
current SOA tooling that they will have
been replaced by mashups using restful
services
I just don't see all this composure
engineered its well and you can't tell
when you should use when should I be
using B pal for WS and when should I be
using Java so if someone says well
interface and service and separating
implementation from that's just I mean
that's the whole principle we just
talked about API first so when someone
says well I'm designing a service well
the whole point I guess if you if it
causes you to think about the fact that
you're actually providing a service and
think from an interface point of view
then it's good so that part I guess is
good because it takes you away from this
whole framework problem again right and
it means that you think about
distribution and decoupling and things
like that so I think that part is good
the problem is the hype and the
immaturity of the infrastructure that
complexity the tools in fact that's
another stack of vendor middleware that
you can't tell what it's doing you know
so I mean I think again the problem is
that the vendors want to turn everything
into a platform game by having
everything on the platform because that
means you have to buy from them versus
buying from for instance an e aí vendor
who was doing the same thing quite
successfully but they weren't getting
the money so let's go back a little bit
in time to your small talk days
well maybe there's maybe today I'll
still small talk Adaeze I don't know so
what is what's the state of small talk
and why is small talk the best language
ever designed maybe I don't know well I
think I mean I certainly don't want to
be the one operating this small talk
museum small talks a wonderful
technology has still a very useful
technology there are many many things
that were wrong with small talk in some
cases some of those have been actually
fixed by Ruby I think ruby has some
areas where it improves over small talk
small talk had the property that it was
the that lets you get things done quite
quickly the programs were readable by
people other than computer scientists so
I mean it's that really true I have no
I've had business and business users and
engineers who basically say well this is
the only useful thing I've seen since
Fortran ok and they could actually read
their program because the key word is
syntax basically gave them a kind of DSL
join the classes so they could get a DSL
fairly quickly by appropriately naming
and they found that to be pretty
friendly and useful so it was a very
good technology for doing that I had
lots of problems as well and I certainly
you know I I think his it's always
important to think how you could do
better than how you who wants to go
backwards in time is one of the reasons
that small talk wasn't accepted in the
mainstream the fact that maybe VM
technology wasn't there yet in terms of
performance scalability or was that not
an issue no it's not an issue I mean
small talk VM performance was always
very competitive and arguably it took
years for the job of the in performance
to even catch up the reason that small
talk was eclipsed in the market was very
simple it was that it wasn't intended to
sell clips no okay something else there
but I think I will pass the the basic
reason was that those who were competing
against Microsoft hoped that Java OS
would actually be give them a position
in the client so IBM and others were
losing their position on the client and
very concerned so the decision for Java
was really about javo s not about
programming applications in Java it just
happened that because the JVM JVM is
more challenging to implement dynamic
languages on and largely the sun
marketing message you know so java
became a weed language which killed off
all other languages as a side effect but
there was you know I mean there were
there were lots of ways to be able to
implement and we are finally seeing now
that people with with JRuby and things
like that are doing decent
implementations and the machines are a
lot faster too so you know the issues of
performance are not really so critical
yeah yeah I think that's an interesting
trend today that that in the Java land
there is this perceived separation
between platform and language and people
basically agree that the language is at
the end of its time kind of and and the
platform isn't yeah well because so many
people have
yeah and the vendors have no other
platform right I mean so they have to
make it work but I think there's a lot
of people who see in fact web services
in some cases is a is a example of
trying to move to something it's above
the level of the Java language yeah move
away from language to protocols in some
sense right so you already mentioned
Ruby do you think it's a worthy
successor to small talk what are the
commonalities what what makes it so nice
in that context I think ruby has the
characteristic that you know has a
uniform object notion so you know
everything is an object has a syntax
it's a little more friendly than not as
not as friendly as I as the small talk
stamp tax but it doesn't look like see
all the time so I think it's more
readable when you embed another language
in it right has some nice concepts in
terms of Ruby in particular has nice
concepts in terms of mix-ins and things
like that and lots of errors and things
like that that are that are interesting
meta programming is a sort of mixed
blessing because most people don't know
when to use it
I think it's overused and and I don't
think I I know I don't think it's
overused in Ruby I think it it can be
dangerous when it leaks I mean that the
kind of problem is that you know if you
you know rails for example I don't
looked at the recent implementations you
did a lot of since I metaprogramming and
redefined a bunch of fairly key stuff
that was in object which is fine if if
you're the implementer of rails the
problem is if someone can read the code
they may assume that that's a pattern
that they should use in their
application code which would be
inappropriate we had problem in small
talk in many ways too it's also in C++
if use template metaprogramming to do
some performance optimization within
boost for example if people actually
have to see it or see cryptic error
messages that come from some compiler
compiler hiccup
then that's a spill out I think it's the
fact that you don't we don't make it
clear when you cross the line so we
really like to know when you're doing
reflective programming you you might you
really like to write that code in a
different color or something like that
how people are clear that yeah this is
no this is not something that you should
do now scary code begins here I
discussed with Eric gamma this morning
about some
similar setting things and one thing we
discussed was refactoring for dynamic
languages is it true that well small
talk had all objects in one big bucket
in the in the how do you say this in the
in-memory object space and the the
editing tools were in the same space so
if you as an IDE wanted to know what an
object can do you just ask the object by
sending it a message so it wasn't text
analysis or any of that stuff right no
no that's right that's the the the nice
thing is small talk and like most list
systems had an internal representation
of the program at all times so you could
actually look at it and in fact that's
what the meta object protocols let you
do you could actually look at yourself
within some some things we cheated on so
you really couldn't it looked like you
could and Ruby doesn't have that you
don't have the IDE that has the objects
live in memories I thought that was a
big difference in how you would build a
tooling for it
well I think but I think one of the
lessons from small talk and certainly
when we do to embedded small talk and
cross development and certainly built
via Java was built in small talk you
know you realize it's a good thing to
separate your development environment in
some sense from your execution
environment because things can leak
right right okay so I think for instance
you could easily go along and create
things on the fly in small talk which
you can in JavaScript as well if you and
if you save them you don't remember that
the you actually created these objects
so there's there's no declarations for
them you're dependent on global stuff or
things right a min that you just
introduced because they're in your
workspace
I think separation is is nice but being
able to play with your program you know
Dan Ingalls has just demonstrated that
with his new lively stuff as well -
which Suns announced this thing called
lively which is open source and
basically is implemented a lot of the
squeak stuff object inspectors and the
more fake user interface and far over
you know for JavaScript oh okay and then
it runs on a JavaScript PM + SVG ISO so
I you know I think the the workspace
concept was certainly a big thing
although in every developer we did move
act during and we weren't in memory and
those sorts of things but certainly that
was one of the things that makes it
makes it in some cases easier than just
working on the text
and I think that is one of the problems
with with IDs and performance and a lot
of the issues is because they don't work
on a they have to kind of reparse and
write a lot of this stuff and so that
makes the IDS bloated and complicated
because they have to redo that work all
the time yeah I was I was about to ask
you about today's development tools
after all I mean just to do some history
here you're the guy who who facilitated
and probably shouldn't say invented but
kind of made sure that eclipses existed
maybe you can tell us a little bit about
that background and then tell us about
what do you think about the tool
environment these days well I mean
certainly you know the eclipse was built
by an incredibly talented team yes evil
and I had the privilege to work with
them but the real issue is that IBM
needed in order to get past the Sun Fudd
because we implemented visual age for
Java in small talk we realized that we
had to have an ID that was implemented
in Java for marketing reasons if no
other that we would not ever get the
blessing of Sun oh you know we couldn't
get this binning coffee cup and would
always do whatever you know so we
decided to implement it you know what
became Eclipse and we was at that time
oti already IBM at that time oh it was
that a decision was made at we were in
IBM at that point but I understand that
oti actually we ran as a separate
company for seven years was a
wholly-owned I be M subsidiary ok but
that decision was made of course in
collaboration with sure with IBM that
this was the right thing to do and a lot
of IBM people arguably you know 70% of
the people who actually involved with
Eclipse me were people from outside of
oti and IBM errs who maybe came into the
OT I kind of a lab environment and it
was done in a very compressed time scale
had to be done very quickly and you know
we tried to provide you know and the
development team tried to provide a
visual aid small talk like development
experience because we that we have we
our customers were used to having an
inter
active environment where they could
compile and test things live and so on
and so in the beginning that wasn't so
difficult but then between Java just
after the first version of Java
you know nested classes unless that was
implemented and that meant all the
incremental compilation is very very
hard because you can't just use local
scopes you have to you know and so the
dependency management everything like
that inside the compilers and things
like that became much more challenging
and so it you know it it evolved out of
that and you know it was incredibly
successful thanks to a lot of people in
the small talk community and others who
kind of embraced the idea and and I
think open sourcing certainly had a big
big help in that and working with
universities and so on so you know today
it's you know your legacy IDE right so
you think it's too big too much of a
thing or I mean well yeah I think it is
I mean I think it takes up too much
space on your desktop you have to put up
with all these classes and all this does
it very complicated very few people know
how to use it proficiently part of that
is just due to Java itself and the huge
Java class libraries but I mean I think
you know like anything else if you were
building something new today you you
know I only think only a fool would
build something the same way they did it
the latter time you benefited from the
experience yeah I think a lot of your
arguments is about complexity versus
simplicity and in the bar recently we
talked about I said something like if we
now went back to Lisp people wouldn't
like to do this because if the language
is like too simplistic and you then said
well what what's the limitation for some
is is is as an Enlightenment is
something good for others so do do you
think there needs to be a a language
that is smaller that has moral thuggin
or concepts like Lisp or small talk that
lets us do more things with less complex
initial building blocks so the short
answer is very much I think you know
what we need to do is find the
find those that the essence of good
language design is trying to leave out
more things and try and make things more
consistent yeah that's a very hard
problem but I think to the extent that
one one only has a few ways to do things
and they behave consistently that word
that means you can count on them in the
and higher level that language than the
fewer lines of code and in the end K
lock skill right the more code you have
the more code you have to maintain the
more complicated is the harder is to
refactor you know and I think so
anything that allows programs to be
written quickly changed quickly tends to
lead to productivity and better quality
in my experience so that the relist bus
will say that there is nothing like Lisp
and there will be nothing like Lisp so
do you think it is Lisp and it will be
Lisp or what do you think is there a
language on the horizon or or trends on
the horizon where you see this kind of
approach implemented all I mean there
are lots of niche languages in the
inside of companies so I think I think
if you actually look at what people are
doing they're trying to unify so I think
most anyone who's used several of these
languages will tell you that there's
there's things that they when they're in
another language they really really miss
so I mean people who only program in one
language of course you know that they're
they only play one instrument so you
know I can understand them the cognitive
load with switching is hard but if
you've talked to people who have used
several different languages they can
tell you about well you know this is
great but I really if we had this other
feature from this language this this
problem would be way simpler wait yeah
Scala seems to me to go in that
direction a little bit it has functional
stuff it has pattern matching from lispy
languages it has type inference still
statically typed so it looks to me quite
promising well I think I I don't know
Scala okay I'm going to go to the
tutorial at a coop okay I couldn't make
it here but but I'm looking forward to I
just spoke to Martin order ski and I
hope that he can do it again and Annie
coop I think it's interesting language I
think is very complicate
that's true nobody one's called it
appeal one of our times well yeah I
guess it's cleaner than that but III
think that the type systems are very
very complicated and so I think the
ideal language from my perspective is a
language which takes the best from small
talk set L scheme in APL mm-hmm APL yep
okay well because it turns out that
there are lots of things that that you
know the APL operations are very very
convenient and very efficient both
execution for expressing certain things
know not arguing that I would take the
APL since no but you know there's lots
of cases where you know that's a very
compact and efficient expression and
appscript for example is a small talk
done for the for the Mac for scripting
the user interface classes which
actually extends some extend small talk
by defining something called a message
pattern so that you can actually do APL
style programming in an in an italic of
small talk so that that's that's kind of
the so I think there is some unit there
is some very interesting IDs you can
bring those languages together and there
are people working on those sorts of
things and certainly I think Haskell's a
strong contribution though I again I'm
not a competent Haskell program as I'm
I'm a stateful Center comrade his arms
yeah and as long as we we can hear and I
think we were there's again a meeting of
the minds there he's a big fan of duck
typing and structural type of a dynamic
core app with a type system to help you
and I see type systems in the broader
sense like Gil adds pluggable types a
notion that a type system is really a
constraint system that you impose on
things and in some sense invariants all
these things are constraints on your
program which help your program improve
in correctness and findbugs so yeah I
think separating those issues it's
something so you can start you can think
easily and then you can start screwing
things down and
you're saying okay now I want you to
check for this attic for that that that
I think we're getting closer to where we
can start seeing things like that that
would help developers be productive
sometimes I think that the most
important aspect of a paranthesis static
type system is to allow tool support to
have a nice IDE so if I mean if somehow
the the I mean yes of course it the
compiler gives you warnings and arrows
but you can do this with testing and you
should test anyway so the IDE support I
think is one of the really big deals in
static typing my claim is that you need
the ID in these languages right I mean
the reason they have to fill in this
stuff is because you can't remember all
the bloody API is everything else and
coercion and that's all in principle
most many people that use IntelliJ or
eclipse don't actually know how to write
in those languages because they the IDS
are doing more and more in terms of auto
completion filling it in and so on so I
mean I think part of the problem there
is in fact that languages have all that
complexity so static typing has its
place if you don't know what you're
doing and you're doing it for the second
or third time then you know what the
types are okay I tend to work on
applications and new products and most
of time we don't know what we're doing
that's exploratory yeah a lot of it is
have you build it three times and when
you're building the third time probably
you want to commit to the types and so
on so again I think the the difference
is if you're in a fast dynamic language
you tend to do test first which gets you
kind of the same thing you get from the
type system so somehow I mean the
experience is in the programming and
dynamic languages is less reliable than
programming in static languages that
that's not borne out in fact I think you
just find the bugs in different ways
right so let's switch gears a little bit
and talk about agile development
especially in the large do you think
agile development scales I mean I know
that for example the Eclipse folks
although they are distributed and they
have these various teams they use quite
an agile process the Eclipse way so any
opinions on that yeah well I mean I
lived that life for many years and one
of the things I do is do large scale
lean and agile transitions I'm currently
doing you know thousand person company
in another four hundred person company
or you know division and you know I
think the reality is that there are lean
and agile approaches I think that most
of the things that are currently labeled
agile really deal with the individual
team and the practices for the that team
I think they're wonderful but most of
the things that you need in the large
actually come from product manufacturing
mm-hm and and a lot of those who of
course came from lean was the oti
process used to be called just-in-time
software which was taken from
just-in-time manufacturing from Toyota
as all the lean stuff and and I think if
you're gonna build large products you
need to follow product engineering
practices and I think the difference
between making agile success and the
large is adding the other product
engineering practices beyond what you do
inside the development team I think what
you know the all the stuff that agile
teams do the scrums the TDD you know all
those practices are great and they
really do help the small teams but that
they're not enough if you're if you're
in a large organization in particular
large product organization and in fact
they're they're disruptive if you don't
have a process for managing them overall
because there's an illusion that somehow
you can take a group of three or four
wild and crazy agile teams and somehow
they'll just figure it out themselves
and you know then that my experience
that's not the case can you give us one
or two or three examples of what such
product management practices are so I
guess our listeners are not probably not
very familiar with these kinds of things
so um any any good examples sure so the
kind of things that we do then in in our
process well in Eclipse you've probably
heard about something called the endgame
and so that's something a release
engineering we call we've called that so
polishing the thing at the end and at
the end and ensuring all the pieces come
together all the dependencies are
managed
that the continuous build and metrics
environment is all in place so ensuring
there's full transparency recording a
common database and putting all a lot of
infrastructure to put in place for
serious large-scale agile development at
the beginning we we have two other
activities one which we call envisioning
which basically takes the concepts of
the ideas from the customer of the
marketplace whether it be focused groups
house of quality is set of techniques
that are well pretty well known in the
product engineering product development
world and produces essentially
prototypes for what our tangible
requirements and then we have a
definition phase which really is a
large-scale architecture API first
design a planning to level a two-level
estimation and allocate work allocation
approach that deals with you know how
you distribute work the teams how they
interact separation of component teams
from feature teams how those things
interact and that's something that's not
typically you know that's not something
that's you don't need that if you're not
doing this large stuff so and you don't
find it at any of the HR literature and
that community is necessarily I know I
think that's the true I am I haven't
seen it I mean I know Mary and Tom has
certainly done a lot with regard to lean
but in terms of the detailed product
processes I haven't seen that and it's
used to be called concurrent engineering
man so there's a few names so they're in
a new product engineering new product
design is digital development you know
there's people who do that but no
there's not so much in the agile
community because the agile community is
doing all the good things about how the
work inside of teams right it's a bit
like the objects and components right
same-same you yeah okay so let's switch
gears once again and let's look a bit at
the state of research so to give the
context I'm currently involved in a
research project deal quite a bit with
universities and sometimes I'm quite a
bit frustrated about
I hit a nerve I guess and you will
always be frustrated yeah the University
yeah so okay you elaborate a little bit
on the on the relationship or the lack
thereof between academia industry
research development how you have tech
transfer and that kind of stuff
yeah that's certainly an area that's
really important for us and one where we
spend a lot of time the biggest problem
is that industrial relevance has
actually hurt research because one of
the problems of you know if you if you
take if you take a graduate student and
they have to spend one third of their
PhD effort figuring out how to make
their top work with eclipse or j2ee or
c-sharp well I mean it's fine if they
want to do that in their own time and
you know they want to be in the
community I applaud that but often it
forces people to use the wrong tools and
the wrong thinking to come up with
really new ideas but there is another
problem is that the best model is
customers laboratory so I think if you
want to be successful with universities
what you want is they want the
researchers coming to you not you going
to the researchers and so bringing them
into your business and having them work
on your problem so in some sense you're
saying two things the one is that the
purity of research is polluted by too
early too many specific technology to
make it relevant and what that does is
produce researchers are trying to
compete with industry and you know in
practice industries already on a
timeline so if what they're producing is
something is gonna be built you know
within the next three or four years by
industry you know it's not it's gonna be
irrelevant I've had this experience a
couple of times I was at the soup so I
was in the dsm workshop domain-specific
modeling and I saw two papers actually
one was last year but it doesn't matter
two papers or presentations that talked
about this new kind of cool thing they
just researched about and actually it
was in my book two years ago and the
book is not a research stuff that's just
best practice and that's one of the
things where I thought well why are they
spending their time on this kind of
stuff there is more challenging stuff
that could look at well it it's pretty
shocking in the age of Google
exactly that people can't type in yeah
the keywords because you can in any new
area you can find almost all the papers
or the history of the chain so I think
there's a lack of scholarly work in many
cases there's pressure to publish and do
new new things yeah and I think there's
a lot of ignorance in many cases of the
fact that what's been done this is also
partly a problem and that there's many
professors and their students are
disconnected from reality poland'
industry don't go and talk to them about
the sorts of things they do so but yeah
I'm always again I sort of attribute to
age but I'm always going you know if I
can type this into Google I can type the
keywords of the title of your paper into
Google and get the missing references
that you don't have why can't you find
them after but I think the other problem
is that the professors always constrict
the students because typically the
professor has an area and students are
in that area and often you know the
professor is the constraint I mean your
father prevents you from doing things
you know and as much as enabling you
right and so I actually prefer that the
students have the research problem and
the professor's help facilitate them so
that when they're owned by this student
often when these research consortium and
things like that are put together the
agenda is it's about getting the money
you know they don't know why they're
there and everybody that's what they've
always done under a new package what
they're doing and I'm sympathetic to the
need for researchers and students sure
but I think the best thing is to get
young people and bring them involved and
say here's a problem you know if you can
solve this problem this will be relevant
to them because often they don't have
problems so they have to both invent the
problem and the solution right I mean I
see people doing language design and
they have to design the application they
they actually make an application that
works with their language and it's not
in there couple right so they have no
independent control sometimes I think it
should it should be the industry that
comes up with the challenges and
outlines a kind of research agenda and
then you have the researchers making it
proof you know proving stuff building a
theoretical foundation
checking how far you can go and these
kinds of things and I thought that would
be more fruitful then as you said then
as then universities coming up with
their own problems now I think it's very
important I mean we've always subscribed
them all the industry is laboratory just
just up the group of people I've always
worked with and certainly though all the
stuff we did at ot I I'm gonna Patera we
really don't find we really can't do
research we don't have a problem we
don't have a customer so xB model of
research right we have no customers you
know how could we you know like this
area looks interesting but we it's so
hard to focus because there's so many
problems that you know if you have some
one of the concrete problem and they say
well you know we don't believe this can
be solved or this would be important to
us if you saw that then that's an area
where you know people can work to it and
you have a benchmark that you can do it
you can even share it with other
University so you can work on a common
problem
industry defining benchmark problems is
very useful yeah okay so to wrap this up
a question that I've asked several other
people as a kind of final question what
do you think it takes to be a good
software engineer Developer Program or
kind of person what is it that makes a
good programmer oh boy if I knew that'd
be clue the ability to deal with
abstraction modeling and actually
modeling clearly the ability to
communicate I think you have to have a
passion for problem-solving mm-hmm and I
think you have to care about the code
you write in the sense it's just not
enough to get it done you've got to view
it you have to view it as an expression
I would yeah I wouldn't go so far as to
call it literature I mean the literate
program that you really are not happy
you want to rewrite it it's a beauty oh
yeah you won't you want to refine it to
the point you want to polish it you know
to the point that you know this is good
you know this is this is something I'm
proud of I've done it and typically
reduce the bloat you know to get it into
a small compact form cool okay is there
anything else you want to leave our
listeners with any pearls of wisdom as I
like to say no no
I appreciate the opportunity talk to
your listeners thank you all right there
cards and letters and they have some
question well I don't know about fan
mail but the darts can come but no I
think being here with Fred Brooks and
other people yeah you just appreciate
that software is hard and you know
making sure that I think mentoring and
apprentice Inc I mean the whole note
that that's bad so craftsmanship there's
a whole yeah that's very important I
mean if you really want to be good find
somebody who's really good and try and
work with them right find someone who
will criticize your work and so you have
to get better right work with the best
right so yeah and if you if you're the
best in your organization you're
probably hurting yourself right three
being three or four years or five years
the best you should be looking for
someone else to no challenge anymore
that's right you you you will actually
start believing that you're the best
yeah okay so thank you very much will
they know to show Dave thanks very much
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at SAE - radio dotnet
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning poly for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license see the software engineering
radio website for details